Hello and welcome to the first video in
my three-part series on rail operators in
the West Midlands. Today we will be
looking at the first privatised operator,
Central Trains.
Following the privatisation of British
Rail, the contract for the Central Trains
franchise was awarded to National
Express, who ran the franchise under the
brand of Central Trains from March
2nd 1997.
At their greatest extent, they
operated 253 stations and covered
1534 miles of the UK
rail network.
The company ran several regional,
long-distance and Network West Midlands
services.
Central train served key stations
including Birmingham, New Street,
Nottingham, Liverpool Lime Street,
Stansted Airport, Cardiff Central,
Norwich, Wolverhampton and Leicester just
to name a few.
Central Trains inherited a large fleet of
trains which consisted of:
38 Class 150 Sprinters,
21 Class, 153  Super Sprinters
, 20 Class 156 Super Sprinters
, 36 Class 158 Express
Sprinters, 10 Class 310s, four
Class 312s, and 26 Class 323s
.
The Class 310 and 312 had already
been withdrawn at the time
of privatisation, being replaced by the
newly built Class 323 on the Cross City
line. They remained with Central Trains
as backup trains.
Not long after the franchise was awarded
to National Express, a total of 33
new Turbostar trains were ordered, with
the intent to replace older rolling
stock. Over the course of the franchise,
many Class 156 and 158
units were transferred to other
operators, including Wales & Borders
and National Express East Anglia. Central
Trains also acquired additional Turbostar
trains that were no longer required by
Midland Mainline.
The Strategic Rail Authority decided to
divert rolling stock originally intended
for South West Trains to Central Trains.
This saw the company benefit from thirty
Class 350 units which they shared
with Silverlink for use on the West Coast
Main Line.
In the late 90s, Central Trains decided
to merge separate shorter routes into
single longer routes and displayed these
in their timetables. This created a
direct long distance travel option which
reduced the need for as many train
changes. As a result, routes
became significantly longer. A notable
example is the service from Aberystwyth
in Wales to Grimsby on the opposite
coast of the UK. There were also direct
services from. Ham to Stansted
Airport.
In 2001, services West of Shrewsbury
to Aberystwyth,  and Chester were
transferred away to form the new Wales &
Borders franchise. Central Trains
transferred 11 of their Class 158s
to the new operator.
In 2003, Central Trains began
using the Central Citylink brand name to
differentiate their long-distance
distance and regional express offerings
from their local services. There was no
dedicated fleet for these services,
however, they were usually operated by
the more modern Class 170 and Class
158 units.
2004 and 2005 saw
significant changes for Central Trains as
they prepared themselves for the eventual
breakup of the franchise.
Services from Leamington Spa to
Birmingham and Stratford were transferred
to Chiltern Railways, however they still
maintained a peak-hour service to and
from Leamington Spa. The service
frequency between Birmingham and
Stourbridge was increased to every 10
minutes, which resulted in an increase in
service to Kidderminster. As part of the
new Stourbridge Line timetable, all
remaining New Street trains were diverted
to Snow Hill. Liverpool to Stansted
Airport services started to split at New
Street to form 2 separate services. T
he Birmingham to Nottingham via Leicester
and Derby service was split and the
Leicester to Nottingham service was
merged with the hourly Ivanhoe Line
service to Loughborough and was extended
past Nottingham to Lincoln.
Trent Valley local services that ran
between Stafford and Nuneaton were
discontinued due to a lack of drivers.
They were not restored until over a year
later when they were replaced by electric
servicesfrom Northampton to Crewe. The
Birmingham to Stafford via Walsall
services were also affected by the driver
shortage and were cut back to run between
Birmingham and Rugeley as they do
today.
When Central Trains gained the Birmingham
to Northampton route from their sister
company Silverlink, they discontinued
their single daily Northampton service
which ran to Nottingham via Birmingham.
The two trains per hour that ran between
Birmingham and London Euston were
replaced by 1 train per hour to
Northampton, which connected badly with
onward services to London. The
Northampton service started as an hourly
express service until it was merged with
the local Coventry service making
journeys longer.
After engineering work at Nuneaton made
it impossible for trains from Coventry to
join the line towards Leicester, Central
Trains discontinued their Coventry to
Nottingham services. The service was
later restored in 2005 as an hourly
shuttle service to Nuneaton, requiring
passengers to change multiple times to
get to Nottingham.
The service between Coventry and
Wolverhampton was split at Birmingham as
Central Trains started to operate Class
321s. Some trains then ran
express from New Street to Birmingham
International, stopping only at Marston
Green, then all stations to Coventry.
Services to Walsall were extended to
International, calling at all
stations.
In October 2004, the Department for
Transport announced their plan to
simplify rail franchisesincluding the
withdrawal of the Central Trains
franchise. It was decided that the
franchise would terminate in April
2007, however, this was later
extended to November 2007.
On November 11th, 2007,
Central Trains ceased operations and its
services transferred to other operators.
The Liverpool to Nottingham to Norwich
service and local trains in the East
Midlands were combined with Midland
Mainline services to establish East
Midlands Trains. The Cardiff to
Birmingham to Nottingham and Birmingham
to Stansted Airport Citylink services
were integrated with former Virgin
CrossCountry services to create
CrossCountry. Additionally, local and
urban services around the West Midlands
were merged with former Silverlink C
ountry services to form London Midland,
who we will explore in the next video.
That concludes everything for today's
video. If you did enjoy this video, I
would always appreciate a like and
subscribe. Thanks for watching and I will
see you next time.